这里，或许就是印度版的樟宜机场。
This might just be India's answer to Changi.
它叫纳维孟买国际机场，
It's called Navim Mumbai International Airport
去年12月已正式对旅客开放航站楼。
and it opened its terminals to passengers in December last year.
整个机场看起来相当惊艳，而这仅仅是第一阶段。
The place looks pretty stunning and that's just phase 1.
等到最终阶段完工，
Once the final phase is complete,
纳维孟买每年将迎来多达9000万名旅客，
Navi Mumbai will welcome an astounding 90 million passengers a year,
比樟宜机场还多出2000万。
20 million more than Changi.
印度希望这里能成为全球航空枢纽。
India wants this to become a hub for world travel.
当然，任何人听到有新机场敢跟新加坡的骄傲相提并论，对此持怀疑态度
Now, you'd be right to raise an eyebrow
也完全情有可原。
to any newcomer being compared to Singapore's Pride and Joy.
樟宜可以说是世界上最好的机场。
That is arguably the best airport in the world.
不过别忘了，樟宜在成为民用机场之前，很长一段时间只是个军用空军基地。
But don't forget that Changi was a military air base
纳维孟买的工程师们压根儿没有在空军基地上建机场的机会——
long before it became a civilian facility.
他们面对的现实截然不同。
The engineers behind Navi Mumbai could only dream
of building on an air base. Their reality was entirely different.
他们的任务，是在一片布满不稳定滩涂的沼泽地上
They were tasked with building an airport on a swamp covered in unstable mud flats,
建造一座机场——这片地里还有一座大山，
a giant hill,
以及一条从中间穿过的河流。
and a river flowing right through the middle of it.
纳维孟买国际机场的效果图看起来无比震撼，
While the renders of Navi Mumbai International look spectacular,
但这座机场的选址，简直就是一场噩梦。
this airport's location has been an absolute nightmare.
印度拥有全球增速最快的航空市场之一，
India has one of the fastest growing aviation sectors on the planet
仅次于中国和美国。
behind only China and the US.
在总理纳伦德拉·莫迪大力推进印度交通基础设施升级的背景下，
The number of operational airports in the country has doubled in the last decade
全国在用机场数量在过去十年里翻了一番。
as Prime Minister Narendra Modi looks set to overhaul India's travel infrastructure.
然而，作为印度金融中心的孟买，配套资源却严重不足。
Mumbai, its financial powerhouse is under resourced.
世界上许多知名大城市都拥有多座主要机场——
A number of the world's most prominent cities feature multiple major airports.
伦敦、纽约、东京，莫不如此。
Think London, New York or Tokyo.
这对入境旅客数量、商务出行以及货运来说，显然都至关重要。
And that's obviously crucial for visitor numbers, business trips and cargo.
就拿伦敦来说吧。
Let's take London for example.
伦敦有六座主要机场，2024年合计接待了高达1.77亿名旅客。而孟买历史上一直只有一座主要机场。
The city is serviced by six major airports. All of those combined handled a whopping 177 million passengers in 2024. Mumbai, however, has historically had just one major airport.
这就好比伦敦只有希思罗一座机场——每年白白错过近1亿旅客。
That would be like London having just Heathrow. The city would miss out on nearly 100 million passengers every year.
考虑到印度航空市场的快速增长，
And given that rapidly growing aviation sector in India,
这个国家迫切需要提升金融首都的航空承载能力。
the country is desperate to improve capacity to its financial capital.
当局给出的答案听起来很简单——
The answer authorities came up with was simple.
在孟买再建一座主要机场。
a second major airport in Mumbai.
但把这种规模的想法落地，远没有灵光乍现那一刻来得轻松。
But executing an idea of this scale
孟买第二大机场计划面临的最大难题，
is rarely as straightforward as having the epiphany itself. The biggest problem faced by Mumbai's second big airport plan
是大城市普遍存在的共同困境：空间不足。
is experienced by major cities all around the world. The lack of space.
看看现在的孟买机场，已经处于满负荷状态。
Just take a look at Mumbai airport which is already at capacity.
这边的一号航站楼正在翻新改造，
Terminal one over here is going through a redevelopment,
但扩大占地面积的空间实在有限。
but there isn't exactly a lot of scope for expanding the footprints.
四面八方都是密集的居民区，
On every side, there are densely packed communities
搬迁难度极大——
that would be a nightmare to move,
当然，他们也不是没尝试过。
and it's not like they didn't try.
二号航站楼就是最好的证据。
That evidence can be found over at Terminal 2.
这里的候机廊是不对称的。
The concourses here are asymmetrical.
最初的规划是两边等长，
The initial plan was for them to be the same length,
但由于在迁移机场边界社区时遭遇重重阻力，
but because of the challenges faced in moving communities on the airport boundary,
第二条候机廊不得不重新设计。
the second concourse had to be redesigned.
看起来像是被截断了——
It looks like it's been cut off
这自然也限制了可用登机口的数量。
and that obviously limits the number of gates that are available.
另外，由于跑道相互交叉，飞机起降也受到严格限制。
Air traffic is also pretty restricted because of the intersecting runways.
现有设计导致两条跑道无法同时起降飞机。
The design stops planes landing and taking off
on each strip at the same time.
而且正如我们之前提到的，
And as we pointed out,
附近根本没有空间再建平行跑道。
it's not like there's a lot of space to build parallel runways elsewhere.
结果就是，孟买每年白白流失数百万旅客和大量货物，
The result is that Mumbai is missing out on potentially millions of passengers and tons of cargo every year,
这座城市的核心机场真的已经到了亟需援助的地步。
and the city's key airport really is crying out for help.
但显然，大规模扩建是行不通的，
But clearly a major expansion is out of the question,
在市中心附近新建一座大型机场也同样不现实。
as is constructing a massive new airport anywhere near the city center.
那出路在哪里？
So where do you go?
经过长达10年的选址，再加上3年的土地收购，
Well, after a 10year search and then a further 3 years spent buying up land,
当局最终相中了这里——距离孟买老商业中心约40公里的纳维孟买。
officials ended up here.
It's about 40 km away from the old commercial center of Mumbai over in Nav'i Mumbai.
顺应近十年来的流行趋势，
In what's become a growing trend over the last decade,
纳维孟买国际机场选址于海岸边。
the Nav'i Mumbai international site is on the coast.
这意味着机场主要建在填海造地的土地上，
That means it's built largely on reclaimed land
前期准备工作量极为庞大。
and that's required a lot of preparation.
好了，在今天的视频继续深入之前，
Now, before we go any further with today's video,
我必须先暂停一下——
we need to stop everything
因为我有一个超级重大的消息，终于可以公开了！
because I have got some very big news that I am finally allowed to share.
去年，企鹅兰登书屋问我有没有兴趣写一本书，
Last year, Penguin Random House asked me if I'd like to write a book.
我答应了。
I said yes.
书已经写完了，就是这本！
I've written a book and here it is.
书名叫《超级工程：改变世界的10大超级建造项目》（Mega Builds: 10 Colossal Construction Projects That Will Change World）。
It is called Mega Builds: 10 Colossal Construction Projects That Will Change World.
过去10年，
Over the last 10 years,
我有幸近距离见证了地球上一些最令人叹为观止的建设项目，
I have had a front row seat to some of this planet's most incredible construction projects,
它们全都收录在这本书里。
and they are all in here.
我把这些故事写了下来，深入程度
I've written about them. I've gone deeper than I've ever gone before
远超我过去做过的任何视频、任何长纪录片。
in any video story or any kind of like long- form documentary.
这是幕后故事。
This is behind the scenes.
是近距离接触、是与团队的面对面交流。
It's up close and personal. It meets the teams.
是人物背后的故事。
It's the human stories.
是工程技术的细节拆解。
It's the engineering in detail.
也是我的亲身经历，以及那些在近距离接触这些项目过程中闹出的各种糗事。
It's my personal experiences and some of the calamities
写这本书我真的享受其中。
I've had along the way getting up close with these projects. I have really enjoyed writing this.
我的一些朋友听说后，冒出了这样一句话："哦，不错嘛，
Some of my mates have been like, "Oh, nice.
那……那谁帮你代笔的？"没有人代笔。
Who uh who ghost wrote that for you?" No one.
我请不起什么大牌代笔作家。是我自己写的。
I can't afford a fancy ghost writer. Me.
每一个字都是从我脑子里
I wrote this. Every single word of this has come from my head
蹦出来，敲进电脑，最后印进这本书的。
into my laptop and then into this book.
全都是为了让你们读得尽兴。
All for your reading pleasure.
说真的，我从来没想过自己能写一本书——但我做到了。
Guys, I never thought I could write a book, but I have.
当然我可能有点自吹自擂，但说实话，我自己读完觉得还挺不错的。
And obviously, I'm biased, but I actually kind of think it's quite good.
现在已经开放预购，链接在下方。
It is available to pre-order now. The link is below.
预购真的非常非常重要。
Pre-ordering is incredibly important.
说白了，我今后的幸福全靠你们预购这本书了。
Basically, my entire future happiness depends on you pre-ordering this book.
所以各位，如果你喜欢B1M频道，喜欢这些故事，
So guys, if you love the B1M, if you love these stories,
如果你喜欢用深入浅出、通俗易懂
if you love learning more about construction in a downto-earth way
的方式了解建筑工程，
that's easy to understand and can be read by anyone,
那就去预购我的书《超级工程》（Mega Builds）吧！
go and pre-order my book, Mega Builds, today.
在2018年正式动工
Before any work could start on the foundations back in 2018,
打地基之前，有三道关键难关必须先行攻克，
three key hurdles had to be tackled,
每一道都相当棘手。
and each of them was pretty massive.
分别是：山丘、沼泽地，以及一条河流。
We Hill, Swampland, and Ol River.
先说第一个。
Let's start here.
在新机场选址的正中央，
Right in the middle of the site for the new airport,
有一座海拔92米的实心岩石山丘。
you'd find this all hill. It's 92 m of solid rock.
候机廊正中间矗立着一座山——显然，这一点都不理想。
Obviously, having a hill in the middle of your concourse isn't exactly ideal.
所以，在任何建设动工之前，这座山必须彻底夷平。
So, that had to be completely flattened before any building could take place.
施工队采用定向爆破的方式
Construction crews demolished 62 million cub m of rock through controlled blasting
以保护周边村庄，共清除了6200万立方米的岩石。
to protect surrounding villages.
但等这一切结束，工地看起来是这个样子的。
But once that was finished, the site looks like this.
好，接下来是第二个难题——爆破出来的岩石怎么处理？
So, on to problem number two. What do you do with the blasted rock?
答案是废物利用。原来，这座机场有数百英亩的区域建在沼泽地上。
Well, it was repurposed. You see, hundreds of acres of this airport sit on swamp land.
这里遍布滩涂和红树林，
It's covered in mud flats and mangroves,
所有这些都必须在施工前推平、夯实。
all of which have got to be leveled and stabilized before construction work can begin.
为此，地基需要整体抬高约6米。
To do that, they had to raise the ground by around 6 m.
而恰好，他们手头有海量的岩石——
And conveniently, they had enormous amounts of rock available
就来自刚刚炸掉的那座大山。
from that big old hill they' just blown up.
真正巧妙的是，工程师们专门计算了爆破当量，
What's really cool is that these guys blasted the rock at specific explosive power designations
让炸出的碎石粒径
to create rock fragments
恰好符合填土开发的需求。
that were the ideal size for land development and reclamation.
这些碎石被直接填入沼泽区域，刺穿并置换掉松软的黏土层。
The blasted rock was basically dumped into marshy areas, puncturing and displacing the soft clay.
岩石的重量随后将土壤压实，
The weight of all that rock then compacted the soil,
使地基更加稳固，
making it stronger
也减少了对软弱地基另行加固处理的工程量。
and reducing the amount of intensive treatment that was needed to thicken any weak ground.
但挑战还没结束——这是2019年时的那条河流。
But that wasn't the final hurdle. This is River in 2019.
原本，它正好从工地中间穿过。
Originally, it cut through the middle of the site,
而一条穿越跑道的河流，除了能提供一个有趣的水景
but beyond acting as an interesting water feature,
之外，在实际工程上完全行不通。
a river through a runway is actually incredibly impractical.
工程师别无选择，只能对河道进行改道。
Engineers were left with no choice but to redirect it.
可以看到，河道被斜向截断，绕开了整个工地。如果你觉得河流现在看起来更宽了，没错，就是这样。
You can see it's been cut at an angle, diverting around the site. And if you're thinking it now looks bigger, then you'd be right.
纳维孟买机场周边有许多村庄，当地居民亲眼目睹了这片土地的沧桑巨变。
Navim Mumbai Airport is surrounded by villages whose people have watched this site completely transform.
但在这些社区里，有一个非常现实的担忧——洪涝问题。
But within those communities, there's a very real concern about flooding.
沼泽和湿地本身能通过植被和松软土壤吸收大量水分。
You see, swamp and wetlands absorb water through the vegetation and soft soil.
但正如我们之前提到的，大面积的土地被不透水的岩石填埋，
But as we pointed out, large swades of that land have been filled in with a non-absorbent rock,
村民们不禁担心：暴雨来临时，水往哪里跑？这也正是河道被拓宽加深的原因。
leaving villages wondering where water will run during heavy rainfall. And that's why River has been expanded and deepened.
部分河段从原来的25米宽，
In some areas, it's grown from 25 m wide
扩展到了令人印象深刻的200米宽。
to an impressive 200 m wide.
工程师们希望，更宽阔的河道
The hope is that the larger area
能在洪水期间有效蓄纳和控制过量的雨水。
is going to control excess water during floods.
在我们继续往下说之前，还记得那座必须夷平的山丘吗？
And just before we move on, remember that hill that had to be flattened? Well, that wasn't the only thing
需要清除的可不止是这座山。
that needed taking back down to ground level.
地面上的架空电缆也必须全部入地，
Overhead tension cables had to be rerooed underground
以防止飞机与其相撞。
to stop airplanes from flying into them.
经过7年的建设，机场一期工程于2025年圣诞节正式开放，
Now after 7 years of construction, the first phase of the airport opened on Christmas Day 2025,
配备了一座塔台、一条跑道、一座消防站
featuring a control tower, a single runway,
以及一号航站楼。
a fire station, and terminal 1.
纳维孟买机场目前已可服务2000万旅客，
Already, Nav Mumbai is able to serve 20 million passengers a year,
以及50万公吨货物。
and half a million metric tonses of cargo.
但到2030年代第五阶段完成时，这座机场将彻底脱胎换骨。
But by the end of phase 5 in the 2030s, this airport's going to be unrecognizable.
届时，园区将新增一条平行跑道、
The site's being enhanced with a second parallel runway,
三座航站楼，
three more terminals,
以及更大规模的货运设施。
and additional cargo capacity.
按照规划，纳维孟买国际机场最终将每年处理
The plans will see Navim Mumbai International eventually processing
高达9000万旅客
a whopping 90 million passengers
和逾300万吨货物。
and more than 3 million tons of cargo every year.
视觉上也美得令人屏息。
And it's pretty breathtaking to look at.
由扎哈·哈迪德建筑事务所操刀设计，
Designed by Zaha Hadid Architects,
整体造型以印度国花——莲花为原型。
it's modeled to resemble a lotus flower, the national flower of India.
地基采用高强度钢筋混凝土
The foundations are being developed using high strength reinforced concrete
和预制构件，
and pre-cast panels
以尽量加快施工进度。
to try and speed up the construction process.
考虑到项目初期选址条件之恶劣，
The whole thing is a really impressive accomplishment
这整套成果称得上是一项令人叹服的工程成就。
given how incredibly impractical this site was at the start of the project.
航站楼正面，12根形如花瓣展开的柱子
At the front, 12 columns shaped like unfolding petals
将光线引入室内，
diffuse light into the terminal
构成一套引人注目的双层系统。
as part of a striking two-tier system.
其后方隐藏着17根巨型承重柱，
17 giant columns are then hidden behind them
支撑着
to take the incredible weights
那座跨度达370米的悬挑顶盖所带来的惊人荷载。
of the 370 meter canopy roof.
弧形屋顶以钢骨架为主体，
That curved roof is created using a steel framework
通过网状钢梁和覆层支撑，
supported by a network of steel girders and cladding.
每一个分区都像一片花瓣，
Each section acts like a petal
由大跨度矩形钢桁架构成。
formed using large span rectangular steel trusses.
这些钢桁架承重能力极强，
Those trusses are able to carry a massive amount of weight
使得室内柱子数量得以大幅减少。
and the result is the ability to reduce the number of columns
inside the building.
设计目标是打造一个开阔明亮的空间，
The goal was to create a beautiful open space
让自然光透过采光天窗倾泻而入。
with natural light flooding in through the skylights.
我认为，这个目标可以说是完美实现了。
And I think it's fair to say mission accomplished.
但屋顶上那些开口，
But those holes in the roof are about a lot more than
不仅仅是为了给旅客提供美丽的视觉享受。
just giving passengers something nice to look at.
它们实际上能收集并导流季风雨水，
They actually catch and channel monsoon rainwater
同时帮助降低风阻。
and help reduce wind resistance.
综合来看，实用性极强。
Altogether, they're incredibly practical.
另外，我想再回头谈一下机场的选址——
And actually, I just want to touch on the site location one more time
我们已经展示过
because sure, we've already shown you
它离市区有多远了。
how far this is from the city.
没错，远离城市的喧嚣
And yes, moving away from the hustle and bustle
意味着可以有更大的施展空间。
means you have more room to play with.
这一点可以理解。
That's understandable.
但让人费解的是，
But what makes less sense
这座已经开放运营的机场，
is the very limited travel infrastructure
通往它的交通配套至今仍然极为有限。
that now leads to this open and active airport.
新路网已经建成，
A new road network has been constructed,
但目前尚无轨道交通接入。
but for the time being, there's no rail access.
据报道，该区域的移动网络信号相当差，
There are reports that the mobile connectivity in the area
与打车软件的连接非常困难，
is pretty poor, so communicating with app-based transport systems is difficult
出租车系统也面临延误。
and the taxi system is facing delays.
目前确有规划一条连接旧机场与纳维孟买国际机场的新地铁线，
Now there are plans for a new metro line between the old airport and the new Navi Mumbai International,
但要建成投用还需要好几年时间。
but that's not going to be ready for a number of years.
唯一的亮点是那座令人印象深刻的跨海大桥
The one silver lining is the impressive Trans Harbor link,
（Mumbai Trans Harbour Link）——
the country's longest sea bridge,
这是印度最长的跨海大桥，
which opened in 2024
于2024年开通，将孟买与纳维孟买相连。
and connects Mumbai over to Nav'i Mumbai.
然而，从一些郊区出发，
But the journey to the new airport
驾车前往新机场
by car
最长需要3个小时。
can take up to 3 hours from some of the suburbs.
当你
And that's the last thing you need when
即将踏上一段长途国际航班时，这真的是最不想遇到的事情。
you're about to hop on a longhaul flight.
当然，纳维孟买并不是第一个在开放后遭遇磨合阵痛的机场，
Now, Navi Mumbai isn't the first airport to face teething issues after opening
也绝不会是最后一个。
and it absolutely will not be the last.
但我不禁觉得，
But I can't help feeling that after Mumbai waited so long
孟买已经等这座新机场等了太久、太久了。
for a new airport, decades for this new airport to happen.
而这个项目的落地收尾，总感觉有点仓促。
The execution of this project just feels a little bit rushed.
当初花了那么长时间找选址，
The search for a site
最后却选了一块
led them to somewhere
有沼泽、
that was covered in swampland
有山丘、还有一条河
with a hill
穿过的地方。
and a river flowing through it.
现在机场是开了，但铁路配套完全缺位。
And now the airport's opened, but without any rail access.
【哼】话说回来，我们现在才走到这个项目的第一阶段。
[snorts] And let's be clear, we're still in phase one of this project.
纳维孟买国际机场的未来令人无比期待。
Navim Mumbai International has an incredibly exciting future.
在我看来，
To me,
全球增速最快的航空经济体之一，
it looks a lot like one of the world's fastest growing aviation economies
似乎正蓄势腾飞，迈向新的高度。
could be about to reach new heights.
别忘了，我们正在通过"关注建筑业心理健康"倡议，呼吁关注建筑业的心理健康危机，
Don't forget that we're raising awareness
并为
of construction's mental health crisis
这一领域的慈善机构
and supporting charities in this space
提供支持。
through our get construction initiative.
你可以访问 getconstructionalking.org，了解更多信息
You can learn more
并找到相关支持资源的链接。
and find links to supports over at getconstructionalking.org.
老规矩，如果你喜欢这期视频，
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video
想持续关注最权威的
and you want to
建筑工程视频频道，
get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
记得订阅B1M频道。
make sure you're subscribed to the B1M.